Judith Lynne Hanna collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Judith Lynne Hanna collection, 1963-2009 1963-2009
AFC 2010/021
Hanna, Judith Lynne, 1936-
1416 items; 4 containers; 3 linear feet.
sound recordings: 16 sound tape reels: analog; 5 in.
moving images: 8 film reels (4,550 feet): black-and-white, silent; 16 mm
moving images: 1 film reel (300 feet): color, silent; 16 mm
graphic images: 434 slides: color; 35 mm
graphic images digital; 116 tiff files
moving images black-and-white, 8 mov files: black-and-white, sound
manuscripts: approximately 20 folders (3 boxes)
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Field research collection of silent film, sound recordings, color slides, and manuscripts documenting African dance and events in Nigeria, Uganda, and Kenya recorded in 1963 by Judith Lynne Hanna and William John Hanna. 12 rolls of black-and-white film were shot in Ibadan and Umuahia Province, Nigeria; 28 rolls of black-and-white and color film were shot in Kenya, which includes footage of the Kenyan independence from Great Britain celebration, December 12, 1963, and Ethiopia's Haile Selassie I Folklore Ensemble, in Nairobi, Kenya; 14 rolls of film were shot at various locations in Uganda, including National Theater: a Pageant of Uganda, September 12, 1963. Audio recordings document music accompanying the dances and other events. Color slides were taken in Ivory Coast, Ghana, Nigeria, Uganda, and Kenya in 1963. Manuscripts include clippings, programs, and research articles by Judith Lynn Hanna (dated 1965-2009) and Judith Lynne Hanna's description of the film footage and related materials (42 p.)
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Hanna, Judith Lynne; Hanna, William John, 1931-; Okpara, M. I.
Subjects
Acholi (African people)--Social life and customs.; Arabs--Kenya--Social life and customs.; Arsi (African people)--Social life and customs.; Dance--Africa, East.; Dance--Ethiopia.; Dance--Kenya.; Dance--Nigeria.; Dance--Uganda.; Dogon (African people)--Social life and customs.; Efik (African people)--Social life and customs.; Embu (African people)--Social life and customs.; Ganda (African people)--Social life and customs.; Giryama (African people)--Social life and customs.; Gurage (African people)--Social life and customs.; Igbo (African people)--Social life and customs.; Kamba (African people)--Social life and customs.; Kenyans--Kenya--Social life and customs.; Kikuyu (African people)--Social life and customs.; Kipsigis (African people)--Social life and customs.; Lango (African people)--Social life and customs.; Luo (Kenyan and Tanzanian people)--Social life and customs.; Maasai (African people)--Social life and customs.; Meru (African people)--Social life and customs.; Music--Africa, East.; Music--Ethiopia.; Music--Kenya.; Music--Nigeria.; Music--Uganda.; Nandi (African people)--Social life and customs.; Nigerians--Nigeria--Social life and customs.; Ogba (African people)--Social life and customs.; Somalis--Ethiopia--Social life and customs.; Suk (African people)--Social life and customs.; Teso (African people)--Social life and customs.; Tharaka (African people)--Social life and customs.; Turkana (African people)--Social life and customs.; Ugandans--Uganda--Social life and customs.; Wolayta (African people)--Social life and customs.
Places
Kenya--Social life and customs.; Nigeria--Social life and customs.; Uganda--Social life and customs.
Form/Genre
Field recordings.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Video recordings.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: 1. Manuscripts; 2. Sound Recordings; 3. Graphic Images; 4. Moving Images. The materials are organized by the African countries Hanna visited in 1963.
Acquisition
Judith Lynne Hanna; 2013.
Related Material
The Judith Hanna Collection, Michelle Smith Performing Arts Library, College Park, Maryland. The collection consists of research materials, subject materials, writings, photographs, video and audio recordings, newspaper clippings, correspondence, interview transcripts, and materials from numerous, varied organizations. Finding aid is available online: http://hdl.handle.net/1903.1/19429
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research; access to collection materials may be restricted. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Biographical Note
Judith Lynne Hanna was born September 21, 1936, in St. Louis, Missouri. Hanna earned her doctorate in anthropology from Columbia University in 1976, preceded by two separate master's degrees in anthropology from Columbia University in 1975 and political science from Michigan State in 1962 respectively. In 1963, Hanna and her husband, William John Hanna, traveled to Africa under a Michigan State University-Ford Foundation Grant, where they conducted field research in Kenya, Nigeria, and Uganda. This fieldwork resulted in her 1979 book To Dance is Human. In addition to many writings and varied contributions to the arts and anthropology, she has taught African dance and offered workshops to administrators, teachers, and students in schools and community centers around the U.S. and abroad. Hanna's written and artistic contributions encompass a wide range of topics from the relationships between dance and society in different cultures and communities, to aggression in the schools and how it relates to class, race, and culture. She most recently has been serving as senior research scholar in the Department of Dance and a senior research scientist in the Department of Anthropology at the University of Maryland, College Park.
Scope and Content
Field research collection of silent film, sound recordings, color slides, and manuscripts documenting African dance and events in Nigeria, Uganda, and Kenya recorded in 1963 by Judith Lynne Hanna and William John Hanna. 12 rolls of black-and-white film were shot in Ibadan and Umuahia Province, Nigeria; 28 rolls of black-and-white and color film were shot in Kenya, which includes footage of the Kenyan independence from Great Britain celebration, December 12, 1963, and Ethiopia's Haile Selassie I Folklore Ensemble, in Nairobi, Kenya; 14 rolls of film were shot at various locations in Uganda, including National Theater: a Pageant of Uganda, September 12, 1963. Audio recordings document music accompanying the dances and other events. Color slides were taken in Ivory Coast, Ghana, Nigeria, Uganda, and Kenya in 1963. Manuscripts include clippings, programs, and research articles by Judith Lynn Hanna (dated 1965-2009) and Hanna's description of the film footage and related materials.
Container List
- Series 1: Manuscripts, 1963-2009
  - Subseries A: Administration 1963
    - Original inventory, 1963 (Box-folder 1/1)
      Items described by donor, Judith Lynne Hanna. See Hanna's Inventory
    - Photocopies of audio and moving image recordings, 1963 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Subseries B: Field Research materials
    See Box 6 for oversize matierals.
    - Nigeria: Ubakala dance keyed to film, 1963, 22 pages (Box-folder 1/3)
      Log of recorded dances performed by the Ubakala tribe.
    - Nigeria: Ubakala song texts, and music, 1963, 74 pages (Box-folder 1/4)
      Translated song text with handwritten sheet music and information on musical instruments.
    - Nigeria: Ubakala histories, May 25, 1963, 21 pages (Box-folder 1/5)
      History of the Ubakala clan gathered from elders within the group. Photocopies.
    - Nigeria: Dance instructions, 1963, 49 pages (Box-folder 1/6)
      Transcripts of dance steps and body movements of various tribal dances documented on film.
    - Nigeria: East Nigeria newspaper clippings, 1963-1968; 1970-1971, 101 pages (Box-folder 1/7)
      Photocopies of various newspaper clippings about local events, dances, festivals, and other topics including the opening of a local bridge.
    - Heartbeat of Africa, 1963-1970, 138 pages (Box-folder 1/8)
      Newspaper clippings, programs, and minor correspondence about the Ugandan dance company, The Heartbeat of Africa. Some of the items are in French. Photocopies.
    - Heartbeat of Africa, 1963-1970, 138 pages (Box-folder 1/9)
      Newspaper clippings, programs, and correspondence about the Ugandan dance company, The Heartbeat of Africa. Some of the items are in French. Originals.
    - Heartbeat of Africa, 1963-1970, 138 pages (Box-folder 1/10)
      Newspaper clippings, programs, and minor correspondence about the Ugandan dance company, The Heartbeat of Africa. Some of the items are in French. Originals.
    - Clippings of Ugandan culture, 1963-1972, 63 pages (Box-folder 1/11)
      Newspaper clippings mostly about local dances, and other events local to Uganda.
    - Kenyan and Ethiopian dance and culture, 1963, 36 pages (Box-folder 2/12)
      Clippings and a booklet about Kenya's tribes, including translated programs from an Ethiopian folk festival, and Kenya's Independence day celebrations.
  - Subseries C: Publications
    - Judith Lynne Hanna articles, 1965-1983, 126 pages (Box-folder 2/13)
      Includes articles and book chapters about African dance. The articles and chapters were either written by Hanna or in collaboration with other scholars.
    - Judith Lynne Hanna articles, 1983-2003, 125 pages (Box-folder 2/14)
    - Hanna, Judith Lynne. To Dance Is Human. University of Texas, 1979, 327 pages (Box-folder 2/15)
      To Dance Is Human is written and signed by Judith Lynne Hanna. The contents are partially based on the research Hanna conducted in Africa, 1963.
- Series 2: Sound Recordings
  The following recordings have been digitized: SR06-SR009. Audio recordings were synced to create sound during film digitization of the 16 mm film. See Series 4: Moving Images.
  - Yoruba opera, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR001)
    A recording of a Yoruba opera.
  - Yoruba opera continued, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR002)
    Yoruba opera continued along with a recording of a blind Hausa beggar.
  - Ilorin festival, undated, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR003)
    A recording of a Ilorin festival.
  - Easter celebrations, April 14, 1963, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR004)
    Umuahia township Easter celebrations featuring masqueraders. Recording also includes Niger and Oba girls’ dance groups.
  - Oboro clan and bridge launch, April 27, 1963, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR005)
    A recording featuring the Odimara orchestra, Oboro clan, and the women (mothers) and men dancing at the bridge launching.
  - Uko orchestra, April 18, 1963, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR006)
    A recording of the Uko orchestra, Umunwa village, and the Umuopara clan. It features nine graduated drums, ekpete, one mother drum, nne-ekpete, and one ekere.
  - Aba waking ceremony, April, 1963, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR007)
    A recording containing the Aba waking ceremony, an extemporaneous men's group, and the continuation of the Uko orchestra.
  - Ubakala festival, 1963, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR008)
    Recording containing an Ubakala festival.
  - Ubakala festival continued, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR009)
    Recording of the Ubakala festival with Joseph Okoro's group and the Umuakam-Ohuhu.
  - Bunyole and dance competition, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR010)
    Recording containing a Bunyole (five finger piano orchestra) in Bukedi District, Uganda August 24, 1963, an UPC Song for Dr. Milton Obote, August 26, 1963, and the Pabo Acholi dance competition featuring two songs, August 29, 1963.
  - Miscellaneous dance and song performances, August 30th and September 1st, 9th and 12th, 1963, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR011)
    Recording containing a variety of dances and songs including dingidingi, larakaraka, olunyege, and otoli dances and Arachabon Adonya, a song about a warrior of long ago. The recording also contains a pageant that was held in Uganda at the National Theater September 12, 1963.
  - Dance and music exhibitions in Uganda, September 12th and 28th, 1963, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR012)
    Recording of Ugandan music and dance, the National Theater featuring original modern compositions, and the dance and music exhibition held in Kampala, Uganda.
  - Kenya Independence's, April 20th: Music from Nigeria, Kenya, and Ethiopia, 1963, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR013)
    Recording containing music from Chinke’s reception, the Odimara orchestra, and Kenya's Independence celebration. It also includes the Ethiopian Flower Picking Song (in Nairobi).
  - The Ethiopian Dance Company and various folk dances, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR014)
    Recording containing audio of the Ethiopian Dance Company and other folk dances including the Gondar, Arussi, and Somail folk dances.
  - Kenya's Independence and Ethiopian Dance Company, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR015)
    Recording containing audio from the Kenya Independence celebration and the Ethiopian Dance Company.
  - The Ethiopian Dance Company, 1 sound tape reel: analog; 5 in. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: SR016)
    Recording featuring audio from the Ethiopian Dance Company featuring the Flower Picking Song, the Arussi folk dance, the Almaz song, and other performances.
- Series 3: Graphic Images, 1963
  - Hanna’s African Trip: January –December, 212 35 mm color slides (Box 3)
    PH001-PH212 contains a variety of images captured by Hanna during her one year visit to Africa in 1963. The slides are arranged chronologically by year and region.
  - Hanna’s African Trip: January –December, 204 35 mm color slides (Box 4)
    PH213-319 are arranged chronologically. PH320-PH416 are not arranged chronologically. The inclusive months are January; March-July; September-October, and December 1963.
  - Hanna’s African Trip: January –December, 18 35 mm color slides (Box 5)
    PH417-PH434 contains a variety of images captured by Hanna during her one year visit to Africa in 1963. The inclusive months are January; March-July; September-October, and December. The slides are not in chronological order.
- Series 4: Moving Images
  Original films are silent. Sound recordings made at the time of filming on 1/4 –inch reel-to-reel were used to create and sync the soundtrack during film digitization. See Series 2: Sound Recordings for original audio recordings.
  - African Dances: Enugu Festival of the Arts, 1 film reel: acetate, single perforation; 16 mm.; black and white; silent; afc2010021_mv01.mov (Item-id AFC 2010/021: MV01)
    1 video file (10:24 min.): digital, sound; black and white.
    Nigeria: girls and boys from different groups perform on "Face the Nation" dance program. Efik girls’ abang dance from Calabar; girls’ umunna erico dance from Orlu; girls’ egwu amala-bu-ugu (#3 winner); older boys’ ugeolomo dance (#1 winner); Ijaw boys’ sereme igelenge dance; etilobu dance from Onitsha, and Abakaliki girls’ dance.
  - African Dances: Ethiopia's Haile Selassie I Folk Lore Ensemble (Haile Selassie I Theatre), December 12, 1963, 1 film reel: acetate, single perforation; 16 mm. black and white; silent; afc2010021_mv02.mov (Item-id AFC 2010/021: MV02)
    1 video file (35:55 min.): digital, sound; black and white.
    Ethiopia: performance celebrating Kenya's Independence. The performance includes a series of folk music and dances: Flower Picking Song; Gurage folk dance; Buna coffee plantation song dances; Issa & Ougaden folk dance; Gondor folk-song; Arussi folk dance; Swahili Amharic dance; Gemu Gofa weavers; Wolamo folk dance for men and women, and the Tigre folk dance.
  - African Dances: Ibadin, 1963, 1 film reel: acetate, single perforation; 16 mm. black and white; silent; afc2010021_mv03.mov (Item-id AFC 2010/021: MV03)
    1 video file (14:00 min.): digital, sound; black and white.
    King’s market: group of drummers & their hangers-on; boys from secondary school returning from a church service at their school; ladies society; women from Benin dance to propitiate the Goddess of the Sea, Olokun.
  - African Dances: Kenya I, 1963, 1 film reel: acetate, single perforation; 16 mm. black and white; silent; afc2010021_mv04.mov (Item-id AFC 2010/021: MV04)
    1 video file (19:55 min.): digital, sound; black and white.
    Different tribes perform outdoors in the stadium. These include the Giriama, Luo, Wacuria, Kipsigis, Wakamba, Kikuyu, Nandi, Samburu, Wakamba, Suk, Turkana, Thoraka, and the Embu.
  - African dances: Kenya II, 1963, 1 film reel: acetate, single perforation; 16 mm. black and white; silent; afc2010021_mv05.mov (Item-id AFC 2010/021: MV05)
    1 video file (23:47 min.): digital, sound; black and white.
    Continuation of previous recording also includes the Kenyan flag raising ceremony including fireworks.
  - African Dances: Kenya III, 1963, 1 film reel: acetate, single perforation; 16 mm. color; silent; afc2010021_mv06.mov (Item-id AFC 2010/021: MV06)
    1 video file (5:55 min.): digital, sound; color.
    Tribal dancers include the Giriama, Luo, Malagory, Wacuria, Coastal girls and the Turkana.
  - African Dances: Nigeria, 1963, 1 film reel: acetate, single perforation; 16 mm. black and white; silent; afc2010021_mv07.mov (Item-id AFC 2010/021: MV07)
    1 video file (35:55 min.): digital; black and white color.
    Recording begins with a few frames from Ethiopia. The remaining footage contains dancers and masqueraders from different tribes in Nigeria. It also includes the Igbo celebration of S.O. Chinke, the bridge launching, the Okoro clan market day, and a special festival.
  - African Dances: Uganda I, 1963, 1 film reel: acetate, single perforation; 16 mm. black and white; silent; afc2010021_mv08.mov (Item-id AFC 2010/021: MV08)
    1 video file (27:50 min.): digital, sound; black and white.
    Acholi District dance competitions August 29-30, 1963, A Pageant of Uganda, Baganda tribe dance and culture, tribes from Northern and South Western Uganda, Bugisu District Council Inauguration, September 20, 1963, and other tribal dances.
  - African Dances: Uganda II, 1 film reel: acetate, single perforation; 16 mm. (Item-id AFC 2010/021: MV09)
    black and white; silent
- Oversize materials (Box 6)
  Includes originals and other oversized materials from Subseries B: Field research materials
  Series 1, subseries B: Field research materials, Nigeria: Ubakala histories, May 25, 1963
  Series 1, subseries B: Field research materials, Nigeria: East Nigeria newspaper clippings, 1963-1968; 1970-1971, (1/2)
  Series 1, subseries B: Field research materials, Nigeria: East Nigeria newspaper clippings, 1963-1968; 1970-1971, (2/2)
  Series 1, subseries B: Field research materials, clippings of Ugandan culture, 1963-1972, (1/2)
  Series 1, subseries B: Field research materials, clippings of Ugandan culture, 1963-1972, (2/2)
  Series 1, subseries B: Kenyan and Ethiopian dance and culture, 1963